the science and practice of enhancing
human performance for sport play and
life Welcome to
perform hello again friends I'm Dr Andy
Galpin and I'm a professor of
Kinesiology in the center for sport
performance at Cal State Fullerton what
we're going to talk about today is an
interesting conundrum that many of you
have found yourself in and I certainly
know I have found myself in as well and
that is regarding rest or taking a day
off or backing off of your workouts you
see we have two conflicting streams of
Interest here on one side of the
equation we're either being told or our
body is trying to tell us to be smart
right take a day off back off don't you
know be overly aggressive with your
training listen to what your body's
telling you on the other end of the
equation we're being told hey don't be
mentally weak and you got to grind
through things and stick to the plan and
don't listen to your short-term
immediate emotions and get through the
training and the answer is both of these
are true so how do you actually balance
them how do you train smart but then
also push through when you really don't
want to train but you actually probably
should how should I understand what do I
need to know about my body and my
physiology based on my goals to learn
what do I need to pay attention to what
should I measure what should I monitor
what should I ignore what is noise what
is actually signal now I would love to
tell you I have a complete and clear
answer for all of you in all of your
situations and goals and I'll unveil to
you those in our discussion today but
honestly that's not going to happen what
we can do though is learn a lot about
these topics we can learn a lot more
about the physiology of plateauing
peaking and overtraining we can learn in
fact what these things actually are what
are some of the best in the people in
the world doing to measure and monitor
and intervene on these and what are
other tools and tactics that are
scientifically supported that all of us
can use so within that I want to talk
about trying to optimize for muscle
strength we also want to talk about just
general exercise
Fitness and endurance and as many
different areas of human performance as
we possibly can we're going to cover in
this
plateauing peaking and overtraining
within each one of these categories I
will talk about what these things are
scientifically what the physiology is
behind them along the way I will do my
best to cover our three eyes so we'll
talk about how do we investigate and how
do we measure in other words one example
would be what actually is clinically
officially overtraining versus maybe I'm
a little bit tired and should back off a
little bit what is a D Lo versus what's
a taper why do these things matter how
should I measure these things how should
I identify if these situations are
actually happening we'll of course cover
the second eye which is then how do I
interpret these uh what is actionable
what is not where these data matter when
they don't when are they just noise and
then finally of course intervene and by
that I mean specifically two areas one
being how do I prevent these things from
happening in the first place place and
then second if it's already occurred
what strategies do I have to walk myself
back to recover uh to fix these
particular issue so we'll cover as many
of these topics as we can we'll start
off getting into plateauing so we'll
talk about why that occurs again
physiologically and what you can do
about it we'll then roll into peing and
making sure in this particular case what
we're talking about is that you perform
on your best on the given day as you'll
hear me say later there's nothing worse
than feeling fantastic a competition and
then a couple of days later showing up
and feeling flat or slow or the opposite
you felt terrible in your race and two
or three or four or five days later you
feel the best you've ever felt so not
only do we want you to compete well but
we want you to do that on the exact
right day and then finally our third
major category is going to be over
training what is it exactly how do we
predict prevent and then return back to
Performance if at all possible so those
are our three big areas today and I'm
excited to jump in now before we go too
much further I'd like to take a quick
break and thank our sponsors because
they make this show possible not only
are they on this list because they offer
great products and services but because
I actually personally love them and use
them myself today's episode is brought
to you by element element is an
electrolyte drink mix that has an ideal
ratio of sodium potassium and magnesium
but has no sugar electrolytes are
critical to proper hydration which I've
been harping on for years but you can't
do that by only drinking water in fact
many of you will probably remember that
I featured element in my YouTube series
on optimizing hydration all the way back
in 2020 which is obviously long before
this podcast even existed so I've been a
fan of element for a long time in fact
as stute listeners will also realize
these hydration videos were the Genesis
of the Galpin hydration equation named
not by me but by the legendary
neuroscientist Dr Andrew huberman I
featured element in these videos because
their blend of 1,000 mg of sodium 200
Mig potassium and 60 Mig magnesium
really is different than any other
electrolyte on the market and has great
scientific support however I want to be
ultra clear 1,000 milligrams of sodium
is a lot and not everyone needs that
much in fact that may be way too much if
you don't exercise or sweat much already
eat a lot of salt in your diet say from
a lot of processed foods or otherwise
have sodium related medical concerns I
personally use the Citrus and watermelon
flavors a ton to preh hydrate before
heading out on a full day of training or
long hike or a hunt since I know I'll be
losing a bunch of fluids and won't have
many opportunities to take things with
me element has also just released a new
line of canned sparkling element which I
am all about if you'd like to try
element you can go to drink LM nt.com
perform to claim a free element sample
pack with the purchase of any element
drink mix again that's drink LM nt.com
perform to claim a free sample pack
today's episode is also brought to you
by AG 1 ag1 is a foundational nutrition
greens supplement what's that mean it
means that ag1 provides a comprehensive
variety of vitamins minerals probiotics
prebiotics and adaptogens and an easy to
drink greens powder getting your
nutritional right is hard for many
people I certainly know that I have
clients who really struggle for whatever
reason to get the proper nutrients from
whole food sources now ag1 is not a
replacement for eating highquality Whole
Foods but it is a great foundational
supplement for filling in the gap or
needed I've also personally found that
with many of my clients ag1 helps move
them just in the right direction for
eating more highquality Foods because it
helps them with Cravings digestion and
many other benefits I especially
personally like taking ag1 when I'm on
vacation or traveling because it helps
me just sort of stay on track with my
nutrition I know that missing a few days
of getting the proper vitamins and
minerals and other micronutrients is not
a big deal at all that's not really how
those things work but for me again I
just like knowing that I'm kind of
staying somewhat on track when I'm
definitely not making the best nutrition
and food choices of my life if you'd
like to try ag1 you can go to drink
a1.com perform to receive five free
travel packs plus a year supply of
vitamin D3 plus K2 again that's drink
a1.com perform to receive five free
travel packs plus a year supply of
vitamin D3 plus K2 okay so let's Jump
Right In now you might be thinking to
yourself why is he trying to cover
plateaus peing and overtraining in one
episode and the reality of it is it's
because actually I can kind of consider
them to be first cousins they are not
the exact same thing and we do need to
differentiate them but the global
physiology is actually very very similar
you really can't understand one without
understanding the other one so we felt
like it was best to cover them at a bit
of a high level in one continuous
episode now what's important to
understand there is when we hear stress
we tend to think of what I call Active
stress but it's really important that we
understand it's any change in stress
that causes
adaptation as an exercise scientist I
tend to gravit toward even myself I
think about stress and I think okay
maybe you added some exercise volume
maybe you did uh more physiologically
challenging things and then because of
that you got better but stress goes the
opposite direction as well so if you
remove stress from the equation you're
still getting adaptations now what's
actually interesting is we tend to
personify this a lot so we make things
as like a good adaptation or a bad
adaptation we call these UST stress or
distress and if that's helpful for you
to understand these principles that's
great in reality that's not how
physiology works not at all it is simply
responding to changes in the homeostatic
balance that's all that's happening and
so when you think about what I call
inactive stress it is things like
changing activity patterns if you want
to think about it as being more active
that's great but it also happens s when
you're less
active if you go to space for example
this is a huge stressor because you've
now drastically
reduced the gravitational pull as one
example only on your body so this causes
enormous adaptations so one more time
and the reason I'm bringing this up is a
huge part of peing appropriately and
avoiding overtraining and avoiding
plateaus is also managing the active
part training more training harder as
well as the inactive the rest
the recovery we really don't think about
that or should stop thinking about that
part as just a n zero it's not a it's
not a nothingness it is actually active
stress so the removal of input is still
a stressor which means it still creates
adaptation and this is the fundamental
core principle behind why things like
reduced training can cause increase
performance and almost always do and so
hopefully that helps you understand when
we hear stress is not just more it can
be less and when we hear adaptation it's
not just good or bad everything you're
doing every choice you're making choice
to sit down the choice to take a day off
the choice to train more it is still a
choice it is still a stressor which
means it's still contributes and causes
adaptation to be really direct here
there's a saying we have in exercise
science that stress is stress and that
means any stress a physical stress like
exercise a nutritional stress a psych
olical stress an environmental stress a
light stress any stress is still treated
as an equal stressor in the body in fact
your body really can't differentiate
it's not perfectly true but it gets to a
bigger Point here and for the context of
this episode let's really think about
these all as equal stress one really
easy example you might have an increase
in Adrenaline with acute exercise right
acute stress equals stress response
however uh interesting video that you
watched or almost getting into an
accident in your car could have an equal
stress response of adrenaline and your
body doesn't inherently know where the
adrenaline came from it just had an x
amount increase in Adrenaline okay so
stress is stress now that all being said
then there's really three scenarios that
play out here for our plateaus peing and
overtraining scenario one is when that
total stress load so all of your
stressers we call this allostatic stress
or the allostatic load so when that
stress load is lower than our
physiological resilience we don't get
adaptation okay what's that mean well if
we did something that was slightly
challenging but it didn't exceed your
body's ability to recover or to handle
it it basically didn't notice this is
kind of like the little brother effect
so imagine your little brother's tugging
on your shirt trying to get your
attention and you don't care cuz it's a
tiny little tug you're not going to
change Behavior or action because the
stress your little brother wasn't enough
to catch your attention now if we change
a scenario and now all of a sudden
instead of this being your little
brother it's your mom or your spouse or
a police officer now all of a sudden it
probably caught your attention you're
going to change Behavior right so stress
load is lower than our physiological
resilience or our recovery capacity we
have no adaptation this is the most
likely scenario when you're
plateauing okay now we'll get to other
scenarios later that are causing it but
this could manifest s in things like
perhaps you're not having enough
calories you're not training hard enough
or long enough or doing enough volume or
frequent enough the stress load is not
enough for the system to feel like it's
overloaded so it doesn't cause a change
you didn't get its attention Okay not
always the case with plateauing but it's
honestly for most people it's my first
place I go to when they say I'm
plateauing we're thinking okay we need
to push harder do it more often or
something like that okay one more time
not always the case we'll get to that
second case later so that's scenario one
stress is in inefficient to cause a
change scenario number two is the
opposite now our stress load has
exceeded our physiological resilience
and if we give oursel an opportunity to
recover now we've led to adaptation this
is exactly what peing is this is peing
for competition this is a race this is a
meat this is a game you have to play you
did some training we caused the body to
say hey we need to make some adaptations
here we gave it time to recover and now
we come back bigger faster stronger
leaner more focused more energy or
whatever adaptation we're looking for
okay this is the gold this is what we're
after number two option number three
here is a continuation of number two so
imagine that we just continued to make
that stress load even higher and higher
and higher and higher and now we have
greatly exceeded the physiological
resilience
or we even slightly exceeded its
resilience but we didn't give it
recovery time or it's a combination
right so stress is way too high for our
resilience we didn't have enough
recovery or some combination of both
those two in that case now we've got a
handful of things we'll globally call
these negative adaptations or mal
adaptations this could be
plateauing this is absolutely a case of
pling right we we did all the training
we we're telling the body to adapt it
wants to adapt but we don't give it the
recovery capacity to actually go in and
do the work so that could be our second
scenario for blat toeing this is also
now when we start rolling in things like
overtraining or non-functional
overreaching which we'll talk about a
little bit
later if you get to this case we often
times we'll have not only a plateauing
or a stalling in progress but we can
actually start having a reduction in
performance many people if you've been
in sports or competed a lot especially
you know over many years or decades ades
you'll know a time that you can think
back to right now and think yeah I
trained really hard for that four weeks
or eight weeks and my time actually got
worse I got weaker I lost progress so
not only de stall I got worse and that
is a legit possibility that is a
physiological result of this scenario or
excessive stress load over resilience or
not enough recovery capacity a good
example of this would also be injury so
you could have gotten hurt doesn't
necessarily just because you got hurt
doesn't always mean this is exactly what
happened but you're increasing your risk
or likelihood of an injury okay all of
those things are consequences of either
that non-functional overreaching or
overtraining which we will Define and
discuss later on in this episode but
that's our background okay we've talked
about the three main areas one more time
we really ideally would like to spend as
much time into as we possibly can but
the point of this episode is to not give
you this and only this background and
theoretical understanding though I do
think was hopefully very helpful it's to
get into how do you figure out if you're
in one two or three what should I pay
attention to what's actually happening
and then what do I do about it if I do
find myself in that scenario where I
think I'm in number three how do I walk
myself back now I'll try to give you as
many direct examples as possible as we
go through this entire episode but as
you saw from the time frame of the show
clearly there's not one quick answer on
this and that's because of a couple of
things one like I said a second ago not
all stress is the same thing and also
more importantly though not all
adaptations are the same thing I would
love to tell you oh it's just because of
too much cortisol or I'd love to tell
you it's because of lack of sleep or
it's all because of calories that's not
the case there's not one cause of
plateaus there's not one cause of
overtraining and so there's not one
thing to measure I'll give you a bunch
of different options but there's not one
thing I can tell you that you need to
track to avoid overtraining or there's
not one actual official sign that you
can measure that say you are officially
overtrained there's not one thing to
tell you that there's a plateau and then
because of all that there's not one
specific tactic or change or protocol I
can give you for plateauing for strength
for plateauing for muscle gain there's
not one particular supplement or
technology or training program or Diet
that's going to fix all these problems
so rather than trying to cover every
possible option for the mechanism what
to track and measure and then what to do
about it for all of these Ving causes
for all of these varying goals what I'll
try to do is just give you some really
good strong examples in an ideal world
every one of you would have a full
understanding of your allostatic load at
all times so you would constantly be
tracking measuring and creating
normative values for you and your
physiology goals scenarios and
Lifestyles we would use that to then
create what we call a physiological
passport and so as this will un fold a
lot in this episode you don't
necessarily want to make judgments based
on one metric or one what we call
Baseline so not a baseline HRV not a
baseline recovery score not a baseline
testosterone level or energy or strength
level those things Meander and move some
of them are really really sensitive to
what happened in the day some of them
are not sensitive at all but until we
really understand what's normal for you
then we can start looking at what are
called standard deviations and so what
we mostly care about in this field when
we're trying to judge are you really
tired today or are you really actually
starting to get overtrained or you just
a little bit sleepy today should push
through it a lot of that is being based
on well we have to understand what's a
normal variation for you personally
that's where this idea of a passport
comes in handy okay constantly measuring
every single thing in your alistic
environment and then continually saying
hey you have a normal variation of your
HRV of 20% so if you wake up today and
your score is down
15% I'm not going to care because that's
a normal change for you the next person
might be more sensitive in HRV or more
resilient if you want to think about it
that way and their standard deviation is
5% so if they wake up in their 15% off
even though you both have the same score
for one person that second person maybe
that is caused for paying attention
where the first person that's totally
normal now you can imagine expanding
that to things like again your strength
or your mood or sleep or any number of
biochemical measures that's really why
developing a passport is ideal but
that's not always possible why do you
want to actually go about this well if
you do that you're going to know a
handful of things number one you're
going to eventually know if you're
actually under stressed remember
scenario one when I said some of
plateauing is caused by people not
actually stressing enough well how do
you know well number one we need to know
your Baseline if we're not seeing any
markers of fatigue any markers of
reduced performance then maybe we have a
good indication that you actually
haven't stressed your body enough but
until we know what that normal response
is that's hard to determine the second
thing you'll know are what we'll kind of
colloquially they call your load or your
Readiness if you are getting some sort
of metric of your overall recovery and
we've got this passport for you we can
start predicting things like acute
fatigue versus this overreaching and so
we know in the example that I gave with
HRV don't worry if you're thinking
what's HRV we will get to that later but
we will understand that normal variation
versus an actual sign of fatigue and by
doing that if we have enough data on you
we can actually predict this from
happening in the future let me give you
a couple of really easy examples we want
to know your limits ahead of time so
let's say we put you through a 10 we
block of exercise could be eight could
be six 12 doesn't matter and we just
collect data we don't make any changes
based on your wearable data whatsoever
we're just running the program as is
like we're not collecting everything and
then we're able to look at all that
information and say okay when did we
notice drops in performance when did we
notice maybe getting sick more often
were there any injuries that popped up
and we'll start to identify where your
personal threshold is and so we'll start
to see hey okay you know uh this
particular line don't cross this many
miles per week when we cross this many
miles per week we start doing more than
that we start getting hurt more often or
or we start getting less return on our
investment from a performance
perspective or mood gets really worse um
soreness gets really high desire to
train gets really really low something
like that you will actually start to
find pretty quickly where your own
individual lines are got to start with
data collection though in the World of
Sports this is a classic example of
things like a pitch count so in in
baseball 100 pitches is like a very
rough number that starting pitchers will
pay attention do in the Major League
level if you go to the Youth Sports they
actually have very specific restrictions
so in high school they can only pitch a
certain amount of innings before they
have to have certain amount of days off
little leagues you know same thing and
the reason they're doing that is not
actually because they know that that
individual kid will get hurt at that
level but they're able to look back at
enough retroactive data and say hey
roughly we start seeing this sharp
increase of injury once we get past 100
pitches or a sharp reduction in
performance past 100 pitches or
Effectiveness or whatever the metric is
that you care about and so that's what
I'm talking about here imagine having
some sort of information like that about
yourself and so you can start
understanding hey in my next program we
don't want to cross this many
repetitions of squats because over 85%
because when I do that's when we've seen
problems in the past or I don't want to
cross as many miles or whatever the the
metric is for you so tracking some data
to get a better understanding of your
overall load or readiness can be really
helpful for predicting future negative
outcomes the third major advantage to
this stuff is you will actually now be
able to understand if you've truly cross
the threshold into overtraining and
whether or not this thing is actually a
chronic issue or you're a little bit
fatigued or tired as I mentioned there's
no official scientific definition of
overtraining but what you actually care
about is are you overtrained relative to
you well if you don't know what relative
to you means because you don't have this
information in your back catalog then
you don't actually know which means you
actually don't know when it's been
resolved or recovered or fixed so having
a baseline understanding of what's
normal for you allows you to say okay
I'm lower than normal I've been lower
than normal for this long and now we
start trying to climb out of that hole
when am I back to Baseline well without
Baseline information you're not going to
know so even returning from negative
consequences becomes suboptimal we will
cover a lot of options for tracking
throughout this show but actually want
to give you something right now and that
is what I call my MVP or minimal viable
solution something I think most people
could do for free or basically no cost
so start off measure something every day
or most days in three different areas
area one is pick something that is
objective this could be a scale your
body weight it could be a uh HRV marker
or a resting heart rate or a respiratory
rate or C2 something that is about your
body that is not your perception so
that's your objective marker number two
pick a subjective marker this could be
your mood your desire to train your
energy how well you think you slept last
night anything that is up to your
perception of how you're feeling in the
world then number three is what I call
your most severe performance anchor this
is different for everyone but what is
the one thing that is holding you back
the most that you are aware of what is
the thing you are struggling the most
with is the one the one thing you're
focusing the most on maybe you're
focusing a lot on your training and you
track your running volume it could be
whatever what is that one major thing
that you're working on that is the
biggest hole in your game uh the thing
that is the most key component to you
getting to the next level or achieving
some sort of progress block whatever it
is you're going after so to summarize
all that again pick one thing that is
objective one that is subjective and one
that is measuring something in your most
severe performance anchor or Focus area
once you've decided on your list the
next thing you're going to do is track
each of those for about 30 days could be
a little bit longer could be a little
bit shorter but at least that I wouldn't
take any action based on any of your
data for those first 30 days what you're
going to want to look for or anything
that lands outside of your normal
average back to that standard deviation
for more than 3 to 5 days so one day of
a bad mood one day of a high body weight
one day of you know reduced vertical
jump performance not a big deal what
we're looking for are looking back at
your 30-day average getting that score
and then you're tracking after that 30
days and anytime you see something that
is more than one standard deviation and
you can Google how to calculate a
standard deviation if you have 30 days
of information that's pretty easy if you
come anything outside of that standard
deviation for more than three
consecutive days or say three days out
of four or something like that use your
best judgment then you might want to
consider something that's happening
we were not going to make reactions on U
respiratory rate being elevated for one
day we're not going to make reactions on
my sleep being a little bit down too
many things play into these scenarios
and it's really acute fatigue it doesn't
tell us that we're plateauing it doesn't
tell us that we're stalling and it
definitely does not tell us that we're
overtrained we might be a little bit
fatigued but remember causing adaptation
requires overload so a little bit of
fatigue when we're trying to cause
adaptation is actually what we're
looking for so once we've got that
established if we see a metric that is
more than two standard deviations off
for more than a couple of days then you
might take action immediately you're
following the program and you just start
really falling off a cliff and again as
a scientist I'm actually using a pretty
strong definition here which is two
standard deviations off my 30day Norm
what I'm trying to get the point at here
is we don't want to overreact to single
days we want to make sure if it's kind
of off for a number of days three to
five days we're going to pay attention
if it's really off though for more than
a couple of days then we might take
action a little bit before that 5day
window but probably has to be pretty
substantial decrease in numbers before
we're going to worry about it okay if
either of those scenarios happen so that
big change negative change for a couple
of days or a smaller but more sustained
change for a long time then we have to
start digging ourselves out of the hole
and we got a whole episode to talk about
how to do that I'd like to take a quick
break and thank our sponsors today's
episode is brought to you by eight sleep
eight sleep makes Smart mattress covers
with cooling heating sleep tracking and
more I've had one for years and it is
glorious I even put one on the bed in my
guest bedroom because as you'll hear me
talk about endlessly here on the perform
podcast there really is nothing you can
do that makes a larger impact on your
health and performance than getting
tremendous sleep the eight sleep is a
GameChanger because I run hot or as my
wife wife calls it I'm a furnace and
that's particularly driven by the fact
that I often have to do my exercise
training in the evenings which is
honestly not always great for sleep but
this is also the case of many of the
athletes that I work with who don't have
a choice when they compete and so being
able to cool down immediately in bed
does wonders for both sleep latency and
Sleep Quality eight sleep recently
launched their newest generation of the
Pod cover the Pod 4 ultra the Pod 4
ultra has two times more cooling power
yet is virtually silent and even has
snoring detection that will
automatically lift your head in a few
degrees to improve the air flow and stop
you from snoring go to 8sleep.com
perform to save $350 off their pod 4
ultra eight sleep currently ships to the
USA Canada UK and select countries in
the EU and Australia again that's
8sleep.com
perform today's episode is also brought
to you by momentus momentus makes
supplements of the absolute highest qu
quality for example we've long known
about the numerous health and
performance benefits of fish oil I've
personally been taking it for probably
15 years or more now you can get fish
oil anywhere but personally I only use
momentus because it's never once given
me a fishy aftertaste and more
importantly every single batch is NSF
tested to ensure the lead and mercury
levels are undetectable for Purity and
safety their fish oil is pure potent and
sustainable sourced another major
benefit is that you won't find any
fillers in their fish soil see the dirty
secret in the industry here is that most
companies will add non EPA and dhas to
their fish oil to keep their quote fish
oil count high but to keep the active
ingredients and therefore costs low it
makes you actually feel like when you're
purchasing it you're getting more fish
oil at a cheaper price but you actually
have to double or triple your dose to
get the same amount of active ingredient
which means you end up spending more
money in the long run or you don't and
you get worse results if you want to
give their fish oil a shot or any other
momentous product go to liv.com perform
to get 20% off your order again that's
liv.com perform to get 20% off so now
that we're on the same page let's dive
into our three areas and we're going to
do it in the way that makes the most
physiological sense and that's get into
plateaus so why are we stalling then get
into well how do I then get out of that
plateau and optimize my performance all
the way to our last category which is
well if I didn't do that correctly and I
kept going with my training how did I
actually land myself in overtraining and
so that's why we're going to start off
and go in this particular order and
we'll get going with plateaus and the
first one I want to get into is actually
plateauing muscle growth and that's
because there's actually a lot of
scientific research behind the
physiology of plateaus at some point
there is a physiological limit between
how much muscle one could put on but the
reality of it it is we don't really see
that happen very often
scientifically caveat of course there's
not extensive amounts of randomized
control trials on world champion
bodybuilders although there is some but
the reality is most of you aren't that
either and so for the for the general
person listening here if you are
plateauing with your with your muscle
growth it's probably not because you've
reached your genetic limit though it's
possible it's not most likely the
scenario in fact what's most likely are
a number of other things which is what
I'd like to get into and probably the
most common one is the fact that it's
actually normal most people think
something's going wrong or their
training is inappropriate they have some
big issue with their physiology but the
reality it is a plateau or a short-term
stalling is quite normal and if you
think about the basic progression of
muscle growth you will understand
quickly why that's happening we have
what are called kind of the new gains
right that's what that's not a
scientific term that's definitely
coaching Andy coming out there not
science Andy but that's a nice way to
think about it if you compare an ifbb
Pro or a world caliber bodybuilder or
Fitness or physique competitor to
somebody who's first day in their gym
obviously the rate of progress is much
greater in that person who's new to
training or in their first couple of
years of training relative to somebody
who is 10 12 or even potentially 20
years into their strength training path
and so number one it's normal it does
not represent dysfunction to go to four
maybe even 8 weeks with very minimal
progress for a couple of reasons one you
are actually now slowing down the rate
of progress and so when you first
started it's not crazy to see four or 5%
increases in muscle size in your first
training phase you wouldn't see that
after 5 years of consistent training and
so you're maybe not plateauing but the
sensitivity of measure is now exceeded
what do I mean by that if we were to
take a muscle biopsy of you and we
measured muscle protein synthesis rates
or we actually were to take Advanced uh
technology with lasers and and
microscopes and we actually looked at
the size of each muscle fiber we could
probably measure and see changes in
muscle fiber size but they may or may
not equate to you visually looking and
seeing that your biceps muscles are any
larger and so in this particular case a
lot of people think they're plateauing
because their methodology of measurement
is their eyeballs and that's not
particularly sensitive especially when
now you've gone from increasing you know
a couple of pounds of muscle every month
to increasing a couple of grams of
muscle you just don't have the Fidelity
in your eyes to see it so you may
actually not be plateauing that is the
most likely scenario so for muscle size
people will really commonly see these
explosions of muscle growth their their
first three to six months and then after
that the rate really slows down it now
takes you typically six to eight weeks
before you can see a visual noticeable
change so continue to go after it it's
unlikely you're actually plateauing
you've just slowed down your rate of
growth the reason muscle growth slows
down as you become more trained is
because of the mechanisms of how muscle
fibers actually work I described those
in a lot of details in our other episode
our specifically the one where we
focused on muscle and so I'd encourage
you to go check that out if you want to
hear about those mechanisms but what's
actually interesting here is that same
issue those limiters to physical domain
size don't exist for strength and so
this is why you will see people who Peak
or appear to Peak pretty quickly with
muscle growth but they don't with muscle
strength we don't have any actual
mechanisms in our body that say Hey you
can't get any stronger there's no
limitation there it is a combination of
movement efficiency technique
neurological adaptations some muscular
adaptations but in the case of muscle
hypertrophy we're talking about almost
exclusively muscle fiber size and that
has a limit for the molecular mechanisms
that I described in that other episode
so how do you know if you're actually in
a progress if you don't have access to a
muscle biopsy or a laboratory well for
muscle growth and performance strength
speed power things like that I really
don't get too concerned until we've
crossed like four to eight week when
window or so now if you're a little bit
less trained I'm thinking more towards
that 4 we line but if you're really
really highly trained I'm looking more
towards the 8we timeline which is to say
if you're really really really really
trained say an Olympic caliber athlete
or you many years of focused well
programmed strength training background
and you're training hard for seven or
eight straight weeks and we've seen no
progress in performance now I'm going to
be concerned you're at a plateau but if
that's you and you're three or four
weeks in and we haven't gotten any
stronger yet I'm not particularly
concerned because that rate of
improvement is small that said if you
are new to training and you are four
five 6 weeks in and we haven't seen
progress now I might actually be
concerned that something else is not
dialed in so that's that kind of time
window there so I'd like to turn our
attention a little bit now and talk
about what we do know of the physiology
of plateauing as always we try to have a
bunch of references and resources in our
show notes you can go download these
papers directly for those of you that
like them or want to learn more about
the details I will give you one of the
titles of a paper that I found
particularly interesting uh this is a
2022 paper so pretty recent titled a
subject tailored variability based
platform for overcoming the plateau
effect in sports training and narrative
review it does a really nice job of
outlining the global areas I'll try to
summarize it now but wanted to give you
that actual resource and direct name of
that paper for those of you that want to
dive into those detail so what are we
looking at here
globally plateaus can affect any area of
your physiology this is everything from
your central nervous system to your
peripheral nervous system your
cardiopulmonary muscle metabolic
energetic endocrine immune all of these
areas are affected and influenced and
influence the development of a plateau
and so because of that as we said at the
intro here it's not one area that's
affected by a plateau or that causes a
plateau so there's not one area that is
a target more likely because if you
think about the immune system you think
about the metabolic system covering
every area of your physiology you're
more likely to see benefits by deploying
solutions that Target systems rather
than local and so if you feel like for
example your progress in growing your
your glute muscles is slowing down you
wouldn't necessarily want to go in and
just directly Target your glutes you
probably want to do entirely systemic
recovery activities or Plateau
activities because the reason your
glutes are growing if they truly aren't
which as we just described they probably
still are actually but the reason
they're not growing is because of a
global metabolic issue a global
energetic issue an inflamation issue uh
an endocrine issue that is going across
your entire system so generally Target
systems for your recovery or your
getting past your plateaus rather than
the local direct affected area another
really cool paper that targets the
mechanisms of plateau of muscle growth
came out of Jeremy lon's Lab at Old Miss
Jeremy's done a ton of great research uh
in the global areas of muscle growth and
specifically things like Blood Flow
Restriction Training but lots of
interesting stuff there the paper there
which I believe is actually Open Access
is called the plateau in muscle growth
with resistance training and exploration
of possible mechanisms so we do not know
the definitive answers here and so this
paper just sort of presented what's
possibly happening and what do we know
and in that they outlined three big
categories of potential areas one is
going to be an increase in catabolic
sensitivity which is to say the things
that break muscle down get elevated and
heightened one more time they I'm not
saying that is exactly what's happening
that is one potential area with some
indirect information some papers but
more research is needed and that makes
sense right so if one of the reasons
that you are no longer continuing to
grow muscle is because your breaking it
down more or they are more sensitive to
the same stimuli then that would blunt
your overall growth the second area they
cover in the paper I think is much more
interesting and has a lot more data and
that is the concept that there are
molecular breaks in muscle cells that
slow down muscle growth this could be
coming and probably is coming from a
number of different areas within the
cell and so I'd like to quickly talk
about these things uh right now now one
of these things is what's called The
mclear Domain and such that is to say
each one of your muscle cells has
thousands of nuclei that hold and
regulate your DNA this is what controls
muscle protein synthesis and therefore
actual muscle fiber size one of the
things that can potentially happen and
there's been a lot of research and I've
spoken about this in actually a number
of my episodes of my guest series with
Dr Andrew huberman on his show the
huberman lab you can hear more about
that there but the molecular domain
Theory says that basically each one of
your nuclei don't want to let your
muscle cell get too large because then
there's too much area for it to
control a similar idea is actually
there's new evidence that that may or
may not be existing and so I don't know
that that's definitively happening but
you can see something in the cell is
controlling it and saying don't get too
big because we can't control it or some
other issues will arise so that's one
particular thing that could be causing a
molecular breaks another one uh is
what's called anabolic resistance now
this has been around for a decent amount
of time and it is typically describing
aging related reductions in muscle
growth and so we become more resistant
to anabolic stimuli where this is coming
from is a lot of research that shows
that the same amount of protein given to
an individual as they get older doesn't
stimulate the same amount of muscle
protein synthesis the same thing with
resistance seus size we know both of
those are potent stimulators and for
whatever reason that same dosage doesn't
stimulate the same amount of muscle
growth as you get older we also see
things like a preferential loss of fast
foot muscle fibers as you age relative
to slow twitch ones and we see it
actually differs from muscle to muscle
so it seems to be the amount of
resistance or growth that happens in say
the quadriceps muscles is not the same
as the hamstring muscles so there's
something inherent to those muscle
groups where some muscles or groups of
muscles are totally fine blowing up and
getting really really large and others
seem to break and slow down that process
uh and then don't want to particularly
grow for reasons we we don't necessarily
know so all that we'll kind of call
Collective like anabolic resistance and
this could be caused by a number of
things like epigenetic factors uh
capillarization so your ability to get
tissue and signals and anabolic agents
like hormones into a cell directly
impact your ability to grow this is one
of the things we also know happens with
aging is the capillarization goes away
which means we're going to struggle to
get the signals to grow in as well uh I
me the anabolic hormones think
testosterone here um this is one
actually where there's a lot of
misconceptions on circling endogenous
testosterone concentrations especially
those that get released immediately with
exercise don't actually play a huge role
in muscle
growth especially for young people but
they probably do for people that are a
little bit older and so this is there's
a lot of controversy and you hear people
say that back and forth the testosterone
has no relationship what's whatever to
muscle growth with the exception of
course of people that have no
testosterone or disease situation like
that we're talking you know generally
normal people but in fact you'll see
that's probably pretty true in in young
individuals but not the case in older
right so some other factors that
contribute to anabolic resistance are
things like amino acid delivery insulin
resistance General physical activity and
so on and so forth I mean we could
continue to go on but a lot of things
contribute to this overall anabolic
resistance okay not to take us too far
off track here but just to highlight how
multifactorial muscle growth is things
like that testosterone that I just
mentioned important probably for
predicting or being part of the process
of muscle growth for older individuals
but maybe not so important for young
unless it is clinically and medically
dysfunctional the same thing can be said
for women in fact um the resistance
exercise induced
testosterone concentrations are about 45
times lower in women than they are in
men okay so women have about 45 times
less strength training induced
testosterone response than men but that
said the amount of actual resulting
muscle
growth is about equal between men and
women right the relative increase in
muscle size and this has been shown many
many times the relative increase in
muscle size with equivalent training
nutrition recovery so on and so forth is
about the same in men and
women and so while testosterone is
clearly important for a number of
factors it's not the only thing that
determines muscle growth so it's not the
only thing to pay attention to for
plateaus therefore it's not the only
solution of course we are talking about
physiological dosages here not people
using exogenous testosterone or hormone
therapy things like that that will
change the equation entirely and the
third and last thing here that's
contributing to these molecular breaks
is a new idea called the Sizer Model S i
z r like size and that's really cool and
it basically says we think we don't know
yet we think cells have some ability to
monitor their actual size and will
actually only get to a
certain diameter before they actually
then decide to split and form a new cell
and there again from from some of the
things I've said seems to be that this
makes sense we have not definitively
shown this and and the world is not
accepted this is 100% true but it
actually somewhat makes
sense and so all of those things
combined give you indication that there
are some molecular mechanisms that are
slowing down your ability to grow and
potentially explaining your plose and
muscle strength whether you are young or
old uh depending on your nutrition your
recovery your train training your innate
physiology what muscle group you're
talking about and a number of other
factors so to recap quickly the very
first one was that increased potential
for catabolic sensitivity the second one
was the molecular breaks and the third
one that they bring up in this review
paper is reduced anabolic sensitivity so
now the fact that we understand what's
plausibly happening this gives us direct
insights about what to do about it or
how to prevent it and the easiest
solution here is look directly at your
nutrition so in this particular case if
we know people that are well trained
have a lower muscle protein synthesis
and breakdown which the data suggests
does happen we have less protein
turnover we have less muscle growth okay
great by knowing the molecular
mechanisms or at least the plausible
ones it gives us insights into what to
do about it or how to prevent it so one
of the things we've also seen is people
that are highly trained just naturally
have less muscle protein synthesis and
breakdown in response to a training bout
than untrained people and so if that's
actually occurring we may have to try to
stimulate muscle growth by maximizing
other routes not just necessarily
resistance exercise to back up one quick
second we know that strength training
resistance exercise I'll use those
interchangeably is by far the strongest
stimuli to turn on muscle protein
synthesis however there are other ones
as well and so if we know that our our
response to that strongest one is
suppressed because we're well trained
now then we need to make sure we're
maximizing all the other ones to net the
biggest muscle gain in fact order for
plateauing if you want to think about it
that way then we need to push the
Hammers on every other Avenue to
stimulate growth possible easiest most
direct one here is protein intake okay
we need to look at this in terms of
potentially total so maybe increasing
the total amount of protein intake we
could also look at avenues like how much
we eat per dosage we could also start
getting into things like the quality and
specific amino acids within each one of
them okay that level of detail may be
where you have to go if you are in fact
being plateaued in your muscle growth by
your muscle protein synthesis anabolic
resistance or some other mechanism that
we just described now this is
particularly important when we're
dieting so we actually know 100% without
any ambiguity whatsoever it is very
clear you can add muscle mass while
you're in a caloric deficit this has
been shown many times we hear people
actually ask this question all the time
is it possible and I want to say
definitively 100% it is
possible there's no question there
however it's probably only the case for
a short amount of time and most likely
in people that are nonresistance
exercise
trained if you are even kind of
moderately trained it becomes very very
very challenging to add muscle
growth without actually adding more
calories and so this could be one of
your first mechanisms if you've gone the
protein route and you feel like this is
high enough and the strength training
quality is there you may simply need to
think about adding more calories so if
you are trying to to stay really really
really lean and you don't want to go
calories up well then you may have to
make a personal sacrifice and make a
decision there so that alone just the
caloric intake could be explaining one
of your problems if you look at folks
that are highly trained what they're
typically though not always but
typically going to see is they will go
through phases of training where they
will try to gain muscle mass and because
of that they're going to go into
hypocaloric or add calories and they may
add a little bit of fat along the way
ideally we want to add mostly muscle but
you're going to bring some fat along for
the ride and then later on in the year
or the next training phase they will
then reduce their fat intake they'll
lose a little bit of muscle along the
way but if you stack those two phases
together on the net you've added more
muscle and you've lost some fat but it's
very challenging to do this at the same
time though it is possible if you are
non- strength trained but probably only
for a short amount of time another thing
you're probably going to have to just
become aware of is the fact that there's
some evidence in the molecular side of
the equation here that larger cells just
become more metabolically inefficient
and so if if you really are trying to
maximize growth there you may have to
sacrifice some efficiency what do I mean
by that well think about it like this
most actually nutrients are used more
towards the middle or interior of the
cell and so if you you know just looking
at physics here if the cell itself
actually physically gets larger then you
have more time it takes to transport
those nutrients in you're going to be
less efficient you're going to be slower
you're going to be a little more
wasteful now muscle cells are pretty
small and so you think oh my gosh does
that tiny amount really matter well yes
yes it actually does so you're going to
lose some nutritional efficiency which
means one more time that's why you have
to go extra calories you have to
maximize that protein or try to bring it
higher you have to start you know
getting after quality and dosages per
meal and all those things if you feel
like you've
plateaued I do want to reiterate one
more
time I am not saying you have to
maximize protein intake you have to eat
six meals a day you have to maximize
quality intake to see any progress at
all that's not what I said what we're
referring to here are people who
legitimately think that they have
reached a
plateau they they feel like they are
trained
consistently their recovery their
lifestyle their sleep their training has
been consistent for several months now
and we're no longer seeing any more
progress at that point what do I do this
is where I'm saying okay if that has
happened now maybe consider adding more
total total protein maybe consider now
playing with dosages per meal and now
maybe consider really breaking down the
quality of the amino acids in each one
of your protein servings but this is not
something you have to do day one and I
don't want to make people think like if
you don't do this you will Gain No
muscle at all you absolutely will we're
referring to people who feel like
they've really legitimately reached a
plateau one final thing to clarify and
that is we actually don't really know
there's no papers I've seen that has
definitively shown need for a caloric
Surplus and highly trained people we
just don't have that out there so this
is just a suggestion based upon
inferring what we do have from the
molecular papers and so it would
probably make sense that if you're
highly trained and you're at that
Plateau that just getting more calories
will help but we do not have direct
evidence to support that at least that
I'm aware of to date I'd like to take a
quick break and thank our sponsors
today's episode is brought to you by
Vitality blueprint let me ask you a
question have you ever had blood work
done almost surely your answer is yes
but the more important question did you
find that it helped much I know
personally being a young guy with
generally healthy habits I was always
basically told everything looks fine
you're right in the middle of the
reference range blah blah blah does that
sound familiar I know personally I
always felt it was pretty underwhelming
but the reality is we can do a lot
better here's an example A friend of
mine whose name you would all recognize
was recently telling mean that both he
and his wife were concerned that
something was wrong so they hadn't made
any changes to their lifestyle sleep or
nutrition but they were both really
struggling to recover from their normal
workouts and had specific issues with
attention span and memory and so they
got blood work done and we're told
everything was fine you're in the normal
range and that's because it was but this
is a great example of how the value of
blood work comes from the interpretation
and Analysis and in this case of my
friend their problem was right there on
the paper despite everything being in
the normal reference range one example
from their blood work to highlight this
was a marker called albumin now this is
pulled up during states of dehydration
and down during inflammation which means
if you're dehydrated and inflamed it's
going to be right there smack in the
normal reference range right in the
middle so all I had to do is give them
some very quick corrections to their
inflammation and hydration and boom they
were right back to feeling great again
within days now candidly I was able to
spot these issues on their blood work
pretty much instantly because I've been
doing this and our professional athletes
for many many years but it wasn't until
just this year that I teamed up with
blood work wizard Dan Garner and built
this type of analysis into automated
software which allows us to run over a
100,000 calculations on your blood work
and spit back detailed descriptions of
exactly what's going on in your body
just like I did in this example of my
friend we call this thing Vitality
blueprint if you'd like to check it out
for your yourself go to Vitality
blueprint.com perform for a special
offer only available to listeners of
this podcast again that's Vitality
blueprint.com
perform I'll see you there and let's go
today's episode is also brought to you
by Renaissance periodization if you want
to put on muscle through science-backed
training programs look no further than
Renaissance periodization RP as we call
it in the industry guides users through
effective and easy to follow lifting
programs all through their hypertrophy
app these programs are designed by the
absolute best in the industry including
one of my absolute favorite sports
scientists and professional bodybuilder
Dr Mike isotel you may recognize that
name because I've referenced him and his
work countless times over the years so
whether you're looking to put on muscle
gain strength or both these programs
will help you achieve your goals and
have produced results in literally
thousands of men and women Renaissance
periodization also has a diet app that
is backed by the latest science and
innovation in the fields of nutrition
and takes the complexity out of dieting
helping you achieve your ideal body
composition if you'd like to try
Renaissance periodization go to rpst
strength.com perform to save up to $50
off of your subscription again that's
rpst strength.com perform to save up to
$50 off your subscription so with all
that said I would like to turn our
attention now to overtraining when we
talk about overtraining the reality of
it is many of you probably have heard it
or used that term and maybe even think
you've experienced it but to be totally
honest and I don't mean to offend you
but it's very very unlikely any of you
have really experienced true
overtraining that term is used
incorrectly the majority of the time and
I think it's helpful if then we start
this section by actually explaining what
overtraining is what it means and then
therefore we can get into the physiology
of preventing it as well as in
recovering if it actually does happen
because while it's rare it does actually
legitimately happen and it is really
devastating for those folks so to really
start us off going back to the beginning
of the show what we talked about is
adaptation happens as a result of stress
and what we wanted to be in those three
categories was category two right where
our stress exceeds our physiological
resilience or recovery capacity we allow
some recovery and then therefore we come
back with some sort of compensation in
the Sports World We tend to call that
super compensation so come back bigger
stronger faster more improved whatever
well the reality of it is if you extend
that too long into Category 3 we can
really get ourselves into an
overtraining but this is really how that
works the initial step in this process
is what we actually call overload and
this is acute fatigue it tends to take a
couple of days to recover from and when
you do that you get this enhancement in
performance so you went and worked out
the next day you may be a little bit
slower a little more fatigued
sore things like that so you're acute
you know 24 to 48 hour performance is
potentially down but if you give
yourself a day or two or three days you
come back and you come back not only the
same but better right that is overload
all effective training programs need
some sort of progressive overload that's
the idea all right now if you put
yourself in a position of overload and
you continue to do that so you keep
training you don't allow enough recovery
or you just continue to push the train
tring you get into a spot that's called
functional overreaching so you've done
some overreaching you've extended your
body past what it can handle but it had
a function which means it was beneficial
okay so functional overreaching tends to
take a couple of days or a few weeks let
just to say maybe your performance is
down tired slower numbers getting worse
but you took a couple of days of either
reduced training or entirely off and a
result you came back not only the
Baseline but you got that super
compensation you got better you got
faster this is effectively what all
training is supposed to be it's number
two scenario some sort of overload maybe
a short-term drop in performance or
metrics but that resulted in you
eventually getting better what we're
after is functional
overreaching if you continue down that
so you continue to train too much or you
don't allow recovery you remember either
side of that equation can be the case
you can get into what's called
nonfunctional overreaching so this is an
over extension of your physiology and it
did not serve a Positive Purpose if you
feel like you've experienced
overtraining most likely you have been
non-functionally overreached okay what's
the definition here well recovery from
non-functional overreaching typically
takes weeks to months so if you you ever
been a situation where you feel like
garbage you feel like trash everything's
going down uh you're sore you're sleepy
you don't want to train you take a
couple of days off and you feel way
better you were not
overtrained you were probably in fact
functionally overreached you weren't
even non-functionally overreached
potentially because you came back when
you were better when you came back
that's normal training overload doesn't
mean you shouldn't have taken the days
off but that's not
overtraining non-functional overreaching
in order to be there again you need to
have taken weeks to months off to then
get back to
Baseline two or 3 days would not
indicate nonfunctional overreaching if
you were truly in that spot though and
you still continued to go down the
spectrum of too much training and or
less insufficient
recovery and you now take months or
longer to recover and your recovery
doesn't even get you back to Baseline
now you are really in what we will call
true overt training and so it's a bit
semantic I guess if you want to think
about that it's also very hard to then
document scientifically so in fact you
will see very little evidence of true
overtraining in resistance trained
models in strength trained athletes and
other uh sporting scenarios like that
easier to find in endurance events
gymnastics and other sports like that
though it is still very very rare to see
scientifically lots of documentation of
non-functional overreaching but true
overtraining is a challenge to get to as
I said a second ago there's really very
little evidence that true overtraining
happens with strength training other
negative things can happen like injuries
or performance plateaus but overtraining
is hard to get as a direct result of
just strength training except in this
paper and this this I love this study so
much what I'm talking about here is a
really classic paper from a gentleman
who's probably done more work in
overtraining and overreaching than any
other exercise physiologist and that's
Dr Andy fry so in this and and um Dr Fry
did a number of studies like this but
this particular one they did a one rep
max back squat and they did 10 sets of
that every day and so what this would
look like is a pretty standard warmup
and I think it was on a Smith machine
squat rack you would do I wasn't in the
lab at the time but they would do a one
rep max and then you would rest and you
would do 10 of those and if you failed
on one of them say rep seven it didn't
count so you were there until you got 10
successful attempts at your one run Max
and they did it every day for I believe
14 straight days and they did a
follow-up study they were actually they
did muscle biopsies and looked at a
number of things across his studies
catacol means beta adrenergic receptors
in the muscle tissue lots of metrics
over lots of different studies with
similar models here but in this one they
actually followed them for somewhere
between two to8 weeks in fact I don't
remember this exact but I think they
followed the individuals until their
Baseline one rep max came back and what
they found was so the range was
somewhere between 2 to 8 weeks so some
of these people two months later had
still not gotten back to their one R Max
so that to me I think it's the only real
documented case of strength training
induced over training which that
probably would have qualified
for but that said the protocol is also
fairly unrealistic I have been around a
lot of weightlifters and powerlifters
and weightlifters in particular will
lift heavy in the same muscle group many
days in a row for months at a time but
doing 10 sets of one at a 100% wi racks
every day for 14 days uh it's not
particularly common but that's really
what we're talking about so you have to
probably go to that level of extreme to
induce a physiologically overtraining
state by just strength training doesn't
mean you won't hurt yourself or have
other deleterious effects but getting a
sust syic fatigue to a level that will
have these systemic physiological
problems is challenging to get to with
just strength training so if you've done
a lot of strength training and your
performance is getting worse and it's
not overtraining well what is it then
you're probably looking at four possible
scenarios the first is the fact that it
didn't actually meet a strict definition
of overtraining if you want to look me
in the face and tell me Andy my strength
is worse my physiology metrics are down
I feel terrible and there's these
negative things coming down I call that
overtraining I get it I am totally
understanding of that it just didn't
meet these definitions in this
particular case so no worries there
second one is it's probably just High
transient fatigue you will get that with
strength training for a number of
reasons but if you give yourself a few
days that'll probably go away number
three it could be a mistimed peak we
will get to that in the next section
you're overreaching you're functioning
over reaching but you didn't see that
performance bump on that day you wanted
just because you mistimed it a little
bit and we'll talk about that next and
then the third likely scenario is lack
of available data as I
mentioned we don't have extensive
research on this because it is hard to
do I will tell you from my take I don't
think it's super common I think you're
more likely to run into other issues
like fatigue like joint health injury
before you'll see that systemic shut
down that would cause true overtraining
that said you're much more likely to
experience or get on the risk of
overtraining in things like team sports
or moderate to long duration endurance
activities if that's the case what
should we be paying attention to to
understand if we're actually there or to
prevent it from happening we can go in a
number of different directions here I
want to highlight a couple of things and
I want to start with basic biochemistry
so there's a lot of molecular biomarkers
that one can look at that are indirect
indicators of that because this is
systemic fatigue we see disturbance
in the entire chain of immunology and
biochemistry and endocrinology there are
markers that go all over the place we've
described some of these in the past this
will result or present itself in actual
whole body responses underperformance
performance drops muscle weakness
soreness chronic fatigue struggles with
sleep changes in mood appetite weight
gain weight loss changes in perceived
exertions so things feel harder than
they used to feel and so on and so forth
and so really it's like well wait a
minute what situation happens which we
are progressively overloading and we're
not getting more tired we're not getting
more sore and so the signs and symptoms
of overtraining on the surface are
really the same things that happen with
just getting closer to competition
anyways so it is and has historically
been a giant challenge for people to say
okay at what point is this just the fact
that I'm getting close closer to
competition so I'm more nervous so I'm
not sleeping as well my desire to work
out is going down all of this stuff can
happen in people and they could be in a
normal spot or they could be in a really
bad spot this is why I do think going to
things like blood biomarkers give you
that next step of saying okay are we
actually seeing a change in
physiology or is it really these
perceptive markers these whole muscle
markers that could just be normal
response and it is an impossible web to
completely unwind but I will give you
what information we have right now to
start you off with I'll point you
attention to a 2017 paper called
hormonal aspects of overtraining
syndrome a systematic review does a
really nice job of laying a bunch of
stuff out in that they will include many
of the examples of signs and symptoms
that I just mentioned in addition to
things like hydration can change
creating kise markers cortisol Awakening
response can be altered growth hormone
so on and so forth lots of potential
things that can go on that list that you
might want to take a look at one marker
in particular I like is the testosterone
and cortisol ratio now you'll see data
on both sides here admittedly some have
found it more predictive others less so
I have found in my experience that it
actually is pretty sharp it is not and
in fact I don't think you're going to
find any single marker that can
definitively tell you if you or
non-functionally overreached versus
overtrained or anything like that
however I have found that if you look at
this from that passport context so if
you know somebody's history and
background and you really start to see
that moving it is something that'll
alert my attention and we'll try to
differentiate and see whether that is
just the Adaptive overload response or
if we are really seeing signs that we're
going in the tank and so you'll see
stuff there lots of work on this from
Andy fry who I mentioned Kio hackin Mike
Stone other big names in this exercise
phys ology world have published a lot in
these areas in different models of
weightlifting and powerlifting shorter
term longer term studies so there is
actually quite a lot of information but
the the TDC ratio for me is more telling
of training stress than the individual
measures by themselves meaning the
individual testosterone or the cortisone
so I don't really care that much about
somebody's testosterone level as a
marker of their overtraining or their
cortisol level the TTC ratio would be
way more telling for this particular
outcome more specifically what I'm
looking for there is a prolonged
decrease in that TDC ratio that has been
associated with worse physical
performance reduced muscle protein
synthesis also been shown to predict
worst training progress or performance
improvements and the marker we're
looking for there is a 30% drop so if
you see that number drop by 30% you're
likely not recovering enough now I want
to say 30% drop rather than give you an
absolute hard number because of what I
just said a second ago it's not the
number that matters it's the progress or
drop relative to you and your Baseline
that's what we're looking for what's
normal for you if you drop by more than
30% I know recovery is not enough if
it's less than that it's probably normal
overload and I'm okay with that to
further highlight a point I feel like I
may have just glossed over and this is
idea that a single biomarker or that
Baseline number is what matters it
really doesn't I will explain in detail
why you should not worry about that a
really interesting paper from a handful
of years ago called biomarkers for sport
and exercise tracking Health performance
and Recovery in athletes that was
written by a number of individuals but
one in particular my old friend Marin
fagala who I go all the way back to
graduate work with now this paper was
actually I think supported somewhat by
Quest Diagnostics so potentially
conflict of interest to disclose there
make that what you will or won't but
nonetheless what they argue in this
paper I thought was really eloquently
written is that quote we determined that
a comprehensive performance set of
biomarkers should include key markers of
a nutrition and metabolic Health B
hydration status C muscle status D
endurance performance e injury status
and F
inflammation what they've really done
there is the layout and say if you
really want to understand the state of
the system you need to have markers from
each one of those areas this is exactly
what I do and my coaching practice
exactly what we we do in all of our
biomarker companies you have to look at
this thing in a well-rounded way there
are lots of different markers you can
pick within them we have the ones we use
at Vitality we have slightly different
ones we use in our coaching system at
rapid health and performance you can use
different ones that's fine the key value
I think here is the two things one it's
not the Baseline number that matters
it's how these things are changing for
you and two picking markers in different
areas so that you see something in Hy
ation and inflammation but maybe your
anabolic hormones didn't change that's
really key to know something from the
muscle performance measure changed or
something from injury prediction changed
but maybe inflammation didn't you want
to know that information so you want to
have well-rounded understanding if
you're going to choose to
use molecular or blood biomarkers to
track or monitor overtraining you don't
have to but if you're going to choose to
I would recommend using an approach like
this that they've done in this
particular paper the paper actually does
a really nice job of giving you 10 or up
to even 20 different markers you can
select for each one of those major
categories I just talked about and so
you're probably not going to do all of
them in every scenario but if you were
trying to build something like this it
gives you a lot of information to get
you started on that Journey now i' would
love to take you through all of these
biomarkers and ratios and patterns that
you can use to understand what's
happening your physiology but for the
sake of time maybe we'll just stick to
one specific
example uh for no particular reason what
I've chosen to go after is markers of
overall protein status and so we've
talked a lot in this episode about
muscle growth and breakdown and even if
you're interested in Fat Loss or even
performance you still almost always want
to preserve muscle so for those reason
I've picked and said okay let's make
sure that along our training that we're
not losing excessive amounts of protein
what you wouldn't want to do is just
pick a marker in blood called total
protein that's actually something you
can have measured but that's not the
only story you should look at other
factors that reflect overall protein
status like albumin globulin which is a
calculated number actually blood Ura
nitrogen or what's called bun nitrogen
balance and then overall amino acids
that would give you the most accurate
representation couple of quick examples
of this if we look at something like
albumin you wouldn't want to base all
your information just on this because it
is what's called an acute phase reactant
which means it is actually reduced in
cases of inflammation but it is
increased during during dehydration and
so if you are slightly inflamed or
slightly dehydrated albumin might
actually look like it's in the right
spot despite the fact that you clearly
have other signs of dysfunction
happening albumin specifically does a
number of things it is associated with
growth hormone concentrations although
we don't necessarily know why and so we
need clarity as to say what is albumin
why is it there and what in this case is
a normal number for high performance
that's not something defin in literature
and so if you were just looking at
alumin and you're wondering if this is
showing signs of potentially getting
into overtraining you wouldn't actually
know what number to look for not in the
literature anyways so some I certainly
know what we look for in our case based
on our experience but not something you
would find in the scientific literature
now I mentioned a second ago that you
would want to pay attention to this
total protein status if you want to
preserve muscle but you may also realize
that it's associated with a lot of other
things like total protein intake overall
catabolic state which is the example I
gave a second ago but also fever and
infection glucocorticoid disregulation
hydration hepatic or renal Ura excretion
so you can learn a lot of information
about your overall health outside of
just are you preserving all your muscle
or maximizing muscle growth by really
doing a comprehensive analysis of
overall protein status similar to
albumin you could look at something like
bun now if we know that that's low in
the cases of low protein intake
malnutrition or starvation if we're
getting extreme or even impaired liver
function it's high during lots of
exercise so it could be a normal thing
that's happening as well as high protein
diets and so you can run yourself a
little bit of an algorithm to figure out
if something's really happening here in
the absence of like a true disease State
here's something to pay attention to now
this is kind of that next level of
saying how do these biomarkers combine
to give us insights as to what's
happening in this example if you have a
low total protein marker you have low
albumin and high bun you're probably not
having enough dietary protein right we
can actually walk back and figure out
that's actually most likely what's
happening and so rather than me just
saying you all need to be at one gram
per pound we can actually look at the
markers and say for you in your
physiology in your situation right now
it doesn't matter what number we picked
in terms of an intake we're clearly
seeing blood markers that suggest you're
not eating enough so for your physiology
it might need to be more wherever that
number
is we
started additionally if that if you're
looking at somebody's dietary record and
they are eating high amounts of protein
and you still came back with low total
protein in the blood low albumin and
bond was high then you will actually
learn and say hey something else is
actually happening here potentially
there is some sort of disease or actual
clinical issue here and we need to to
look elsewhere or refer out to a doctor
of some type so that's just one little
example of how you can use these markers
that to can directly inform your action
that's giving you an understanding a
state of whether you're not in this
functional overreaching overtraining or
otherwise fine now as I've been
threatening several times now I could go
on and on but I will stop there for the
sake of your listening experience and
we'll come back to some of this stuff in
other episodes or perhaps next season
but to summarize where we got to with
overtraining itself is actually fairly
rare most likely you're either
non-functional overreaching but in fact
a lot of the times we're not even there
it is just overreaching and we have not
yet realized the performance benefits to
it because we haven't matched it with
recovery the next section we're going to
go into then is to making sure we
actualize and get all the results from
the training and hard work we put in by
appropriately peing or what we will call
in the literature tapering to start us
off I want to go back to the very
beginning and we talked about those
three different states State one stress
load is too low over physiological
resilience and we get plateaus or no
adaptation point two stress load
exceeded physiological
resilience we allowed for Recovery
therefore we got adaptations and we were
peing we just got done talking about
number three too much stress not enough
recovery negative outcomes over training
so what do we need to do and what does
recovery look like how do we need to
plan this stuff out and what does the
scientific literature say about peing or
tapering as we get started I actually
recently made a a tweet about this and
was stunned by number one how popular
and interested the people were in it but
the fact that there was some confusion
clearly on tapering versus periodization
versus D Lo when we talk about things
like a D Lo that tends to be a day off
you backed off for a week or two this is
you know something that can be done in
response to just kind of how you're
feeling maybe got sick that day maybe
feeling a little bit tired and you kind
of backed off a little bit it also can
be planned so a normal period of ation
or program design structure is often
things like three or four weeks of
intensified training with a planned week
or 10 days or two weeks of D Lo okay
super effective something we would
strongly encourage for muscle strength
for speed for power for endurance and
many other factors so training for uh
performance enhancements in physical
attributes is a good idea to have some
sort of back off or planned periodized
approach that's not what we're referring
to in this section taper is a spe
specific time where we're going to
extend that D Lo prior to
competition fundamentally quite
different so that's what a D Lo is let
me now walk you through and explain what
an actual taper is how it works why you
should do it how much it will benefit
you and the research behind exactly what
to do for your volume intensity
frequency exercise selection and more
tapering is incredibly effective at
enhancing performance because of the
basic model that we call Fitness minus
fatigue so your physical fitness
sometimes described as your V2 Max but
in this case even colloquially your
strength your agility your coordination
your skill all those things will just
call Fitness so your physical attributes
are actually pretty stable and
specifically your V2 Max and aerobic
endurance conditioning are quite stable
your fatigue though is highly transient
okay so think about it this way if you
took the day off today you would not get
any weaker you you would not reduce your
VO2 max nothing would change in your
Fitness however taking a single day off
can dramatically change your acute
fatigue some extra rest some more food
can absolutely a little bit of caffeine
or stimulant can immediately change your
perceived fatigue level so if we think
about fatigue being transient of course
you can be fatigued often for a long
period of time but the actual effects of
it are transient they're acute Fitness
is pretty stable and so if we know that
we can say Okay prior to competition we
want to maximize our fitness but reduce
our fatigue so if we give ourselves some
more energy A couple of days or so prior
to competition and we reduce fatigue
we're not going to compromise our
fitness and therefore we should perform
at a higher level and the literature
will basically support that in fact I'll
just tell you right now I'll jump the
gun a little bit I don't know of a
single paper that has ever appropriately
designed a taper program and failed to
show benefits it is really quite strong
the well-roundedness and support for the
performance enhancing benefits of a
reasonable taper what's a reasonable
taper mean and what are those
performance benefits it can be quite
extensive and it can range there are
studies showing up to a 28 day long
taper of up to 70% volume reduction
still don't come with performance drops
now it depends on how you're defining
performance so let's start talking
details so what do we know it's been
well documented a really nice review
from my friends Jimmy baggley and Kevin
murak called less is more the
physiological basis for tapering and
endurance strength and power athletes
it's a little bit older at this point I
think about 9 years or so but it is a
really nice easyto read document that is
open access you can check you in that
paper you will see uh performance
benefits in cycling swimming running
rowing from the strength training side
weightlifting and powerlifting and
strongman Highland Games bodybuilding
even more recent research on CrossFit uh
Team Sports volleyball soccer rugby etc
etc and it all seems to show a positive
benefit from taper and the benefits are
really well-rounded and so it actually
comes in what we call the whole body to
Gene to cell to everything else in
between there are molecular responses at
the single fiber level there are changes
in strength and performance and sporting
outcomes winning more games so on and so
forth so I'm so confident in these data
because it's been done in so many
populations in so many different
Laboratories in so many settings in so
many sports it's at the cellular level
it's at the performance level it's at
the psychological level and it is again
almost all pointing the same direction
which gives you tremendous confidence
that this is a real and is a really
important phenomenon my favorite example
that I'd like to take you through in
detail is another paper that I
co-authored at I was not in charge here
this was done when I was a doctoral
student but it was done by my friend
Nick luden and this was a really fun
paper we did a study in which we looked
at a Collegiate cross country team and
we did this in season which was awesome
so shout out to all you people that
helped out with that is participants
because it's hard to get athletes in
competition to do a study like this and
so we looked at them we did performance
testing BO2 Max Muscle biopsies both pre
and post a 3-we taper in season so we
actually did this I think 3 weeks before
their conference championships did their
post testing right before and then the
data collection actually happened in
their actual races and so when we say
that we saw about a
6% average Improvement in race
performance it was looking at their race
times at conference championships as
well as the three weeks before so what
happened is we let these athletes just
do whatever they were going to do for
their normal taper and they eventually
did uh get to about a 50 % reduction in
volume by the third week what that
specifically looked like was week one
they dropped their volume by 27% so
volume is at 73% of peak then it went
from 73% to about 73% and then down to
50% and they did this mostly by reducing
their moderate intensity training so
they kept their high-intensity speed
stuff their race Pace stuff or even
above Race paace they kept their long
slow recovery runs and everything in
between they cut now we didn't ask them
to do this we just said do what you want
to do and that's basically how they
chose to do it so that's one model of it
for an endurance athlete I already got
to the end here which is to say that
their performance significantly improved
but I think what was most interesting is
despite the fact that they got to a 50%
reduction in mileage per week we tracked
heart rate we tracked all these other
things but I'm kind of just cutting to
the end here we saw no reduction in V2
Max so despite running half the miles
they did not lose their physical fitness
we saw no change or reduction in
numerous enzymes associated with aerobic
metabolism like citrate synthes and a
bunch of other things and more
importantly interestingly we saw a huge
elevation in fast twitch muscle fiber
function we saw about a 7% increase in
fiber size so diameter so 7% hypert of
fast fibers by cutting training volume
in half there was about a 10% increase
in single fiber Force production
velocity went up though it wasn't
statistically significant but about 3 or
4% if I remember correctly and overall
power was up about 10% as well and you
will actually see this consistently in
the in the literature fast switch muscle
fibers tend to be hyper responsive to
taper we don't really see much in any of
the research on slow fibers but the fast
switch fibers one will do this the
magnitude which I I'll cover in more
detail in a second is pretty standard
with what we found in this particular
study and so you're going to see those
things there and one could argue that's
potentially one of the largest
contributors to that enhanced
performance is the fact they fastor
muscle fibers really tend to take off
you will see a large range in the
research as well as in many practical
settings about how people choose to
taper but I'll try to summarize what the
science says right now collectively
basic premise is that we want to try to
reduce fatigue without compromising
Fitness so we see enhanced performance
and we do this by modifying some of
these variables in the following way
first is duration how long should it be
we see success in a range from about 2
to up to 21 days intensity is typically
either maintained or even slightly
elevated now some particular scenarios
will slightly decrease it but that's
context specific and I will give you
those examples a little bit later almost
universally though you'll see about a 40
to 60% reduction in volume context will
change that some do more in fact there's
some documentation of people reducing
volume by up to 90% And still
performance enhancements but again
spaning the entire breath of literature
you're going to see 40 to 60% as really
really really common numbers that
happen frequency which is how many days
you know per week are you working out
tends to be the same or slightly reduce
I will tell you personally I generally
don't recommend going to more than a 20%
reduction in frequency think about it
this way if you're normally used to
working out 5 days a week you probably
don't want to cut it down to 3 days a
week or or two days a week I don't have
data to back this up it's just been my
personal and coaching experience people
tend to feel sluggish or a little bit
slow or their skill especially if
they're in a skill-based sport like golf
or something like that even running
shooting basketballs your stride feels
off you feel a little bit you just feel
a little bit sloppy so we tend to keep
frequency pretty close if we do drop it
we drop it by about one day so maybe we
cut off one of our sessions if we have
10 workouts in the week we might drop it
to eight or something like that but we
don't want to do too dramatic of a drop
in frequency cuz we just don't feel
great after that if you do all that you
will see somewhere between a three to 6%
enhancement in physical performance now
you may be thinking to yourself that's
not much well the reality of it is you
know pick any major race say the Olympic
Games the difference between first and
say fourth or fifth place is probably
like one and a half to
2% and so another way to think about
this is all of your training all of your
sacrifice and your dieting and not
hanging out with friends and working
through pain and Rehab all that can be
lost by simply not tapering
appropriately it can be the difference
between winning the gold and not even
making on the podium it's one of the
reasons why I want to talk about this it
is incredibly powerful and a lot of
people M these tapers and that's what
results in you feeling great a week
before and then flat on the day of the
race or or feeling terrible running
through a race performing poorly and
then having and setting PRS the next
week uh any athlete or competitor will
tell you like those are one of the worst
feelings you can get it feels terrible
to just bomb on a competition I have
done this personally many times and then
set PRS a couple of days later and
you're like what the heck like where was
that three days ago well this is
potentially one of the reasons why you
miss time to speak a couple of other
broad themes you'll see in the research
one people that tend to benefit the most
from a taper are those coming from the
biggest overload if you've trained hard
for two weeks you probably don't need a
taper right if you had a six weeks of
moderate training you maybe don't need a
taper the ones that have trained either
the longest or the hardest in fact
there's some really cool methods of
taper like Mike Stone has done in his
lab at East Tennessee where they
actually intentionally do a week or two
weeks of really aggressive overload
leading into their
so this is actually not their normal
training they even go harder or longer
on that for a short overload then go
into their taper and they see greater
benefits from their taper when doing
something like that you can get in the
details and read his papers and see the
exact
methodologies not for everyone and not
wouldn't work in every single sport but
that's a really good example of
highlighting the point like if you don't
have anything to taper from you're not
going to see a taper benefit remember
what we've been talking about what
causes this stuff what's happening to
physi techology that should then make
sense of who's going to respond the best
to this if you're doing something like
running your first
5k you probably would benefit from a
couple of days of taper almost surely
but you maybe don't need a 21-day taper
prior of that competition if you've been
training for six weeks you've been
training for four years like we do with
our athletes right now who are getting
ready for Paris of which we've got
multiple and multiple Sports the taper
is actually very long because we've
really been training for 4 years for
this approach okay couple of other
things to think about here you're really
not going to see any benefit from
raising your volume during a taper and
in fact there's enough evidence to
suggest it can hurt and so bringing up
volume close to competition is almost
always a bad idea okay one more time I
don't know of any papers or studies who
have ever shown a benefit from Raising
volume during a taper and I know of many
that have shown negative consequences so
volume seems to be the big one we want
to be paying attention to here now in
terms of intensity one of the things
you'll also see is either you want to
keep that or raise it slightly but no
more than 25% right so that is a large
bump right there and is almost always
going to come with negative consequences
next thing to keep in mind is if you're
going to keep your intensity the same or
even slightly elevated it you have to
have at least a
25% or more reduction in volume okay so
if in your situation you've decided to
keep your intensity and you've only
reduced volume by 10% you're probably
going to see no benefit if however you
only want to reduce your volume by 10%
for whatever reason but you're not
increasing intensity you might be okay
so it's that combination that you want
to avoid either keeping volume or
raising it probably bad only lowering
volume by a little bit but keeping or
raising your intensity also bad okay so
if you're going to keep the volume
around you got to really make sure that
intensity is accounted for or you're
still going to run into problems okay
those are some of the really big themes
that you'll see tend to be true across
multiple styles of Performance training
groups and and Laboratories I want to
share a little bit about the physiology
of what's happening during a taper and
why you're seeing this performance
benefits there is evidence uh on every
part of your physiology for the most
part you're creating kinas levels your
lactate your sleep muscle glycogen
hydration I've mentioned fast touch
muscle fibers all of these things are
enhanced or can be enhanced with a
properly designed taper why is this
happening well I actually want to pull
out a couple of very quick physiology
examples one of them in particular I
think is to actually highlight what's
not happening so there are some
misconceptions that I've heard a bunch
and so I do want to make sure we cover
that and the one that I'm drawing most
attention to here is testosterone so one
of the things that generally does not
happen during a taper is testosterone it
really will not change much despite the
fact you're seeing these performance
enhancements I would not anticipate your
testosterone increasing it probably has
gone down a little bit from overload
training but as I've shown a couple of
times now it probably takes a little bit
longer than a two or 10 day or even 21
day taper for that to be increased
however what matters is your performance
goes up and so this is another example
of testosterone is important but it's
not not the primary thing it's not the
king it is not a direct tie to physical
size or performance or anything else
like that so don't expect much to happen
in that I also want to highlight this
because people will often do things like
I think I'm overtrained therefore I
backed off or a fully stopped training
they maybe they got a blood test done
and their testosterone was low and then
they get their blood checked again and
their testosterone is still low and now
they're really confused or concerned and
I want to let you know that that's
actually probably still normal it's not
going to respond for quite some time it
might that's great if it does but if it
doesn't you may or may not actually have
something you know legitimately
medically wrong with you it is a pretty
common thing in fact most of the
research on taper will show that
testosterone is not going to change
during a taper however other things like
your glutamate to glutamine ratio are
increased with overtraining and are
reversed with taper so that is a much
better molecular biomarker of actual
overtraining status than something like
testosterone physical strength is a
little bit of a different story and this
is where we see a lot of benefits I've
already highlighted the fact that the
fast twitch muscle fibers which are
somewhere between five to eight times
more powerful than slow twitch fibers
are hyper responsive to taper and so
because of that you see everything from
Total work capacity to Peak power
repeated Sprint ability vertical jump
height max power and so on and so forth
all have been shown to improve with as
little as a weak or even less of a taper
hopefully I've convinced you at this
point if you do a properly designed
taper you will see performance
enhancements whether we're talking about
endurance or strength or power or
anything between I would like to move
now into telling you exactly how to do
it so what are the different types of
taper how do I actually execute them I
gave you a quick summary a few minutes
ago but there's a lot more detail there
and I know a lot of you are interested
in that so I would don't want to stop
you short of that information and tell
you about the research and the science
on different modes of taper what people
are doing and how it may differ for
powerlifters versus weightlifters versus
soccer players or rugby players so let's
get into those details now there are
three main styles of taper the first is
what's called a step this involves a
sudden reduction in training load and is
slightly more common than the other two
Styles but it's not that much more
documented additional thing to think
here is strength training research
probably favors this style over the
other ones but again it is not a massive
or
overwhelming uh benefit here relative to
the other ones so the other ones the
second one most common is what's called
linear and this is a constant reduction
in load over several weeks and then the
third is actually oftentimes divided
into two different styles this is called
exponential there's a fast exponential
and a slow exponential uh these ones are
constant reductions so if you think
about linear and you think about a graph
that has say 14 days on it if you want
to do a two- Weg taper And if every one
of these styles step linear and
exponential they all start at 100 and
100 is your maximum volume whatever that
number is to you okay so all of us start
at the same volume and by the end of the
14 days we want to get really really low
the question is how do we choose to get
there and what I should have clarified
at the beginning is by style of tapers I
mean we all have to get to lower volume
how do we get to that lower volume is
really determining the style of the
taper so we're all starting at 100 and
in 14 days just to make this example
easy to follow we all want to get to
roughly the same spot now in a linear
taper you're basically going to go down
in a linear fashion and so let's say day
14 you did 100 miles just to make
numbers day 13 you might go to 90 and
then you go to 80 70 60 50 Etc it would
be a straight line down in volume that'd
be a linear
approach a step taper is just simply
coming right out the gates day 14 going
from 100 miles down to 30 and you just
stay at 30 miles the entire 14 days and
so it's like falling off a giant step if
you will it doesn't matter if you want
to go to a 50% reduction or 60% or 30%
or whatever it is the point is wherever
you want to get to at the end you go
right to that number immediately and
keep that pretty consistent the entire
time so you fell off a big step and K
kept that level the entire way that
counters or that's different from the
linear approach which is to say if we're
starting at 100 and we want to get to 50
by the end we'll just go down in a
linear fashion 100 90 80 70 60 50 Etc
hopefully that made a little bit of
sense the one we're not going to spend
as much time on here exponential fast
and slow is kind of a combination and so
we're still going to drop in fact we're
probably going to end up with the lowest
volume out of anybody but we're going to
drop pretty dramatically quickly so we
might go from 100 to 80 the next day and
then from there it'll be more of a
gradual swinging slope so you can kind
of see this as an arc like a hammock if
you will right so we're just kind of
kind of drop pretty quickly and then
we'll slowly curve our way down to the
bottom and kind of meet at the same
level that the linear would have got to
um so the total amount of volume
throughout the entire 14 days days
differs between all these but they're
all still reducing volume one way or the
other there's another thing we have not
talked about which is the complete
cessation of exercise such that you
finish your taper and then how many days
do you take completely off of training
none before competition weightlifters
you're going to see something like a day
day and a half on average some people
take the entire day before off some
people do light barbell work or
technique work and then others take as
much as 2 days off I can tell you right
now in boxing in the UFC
there's never going to take the day off
before in fact most people are going to
do some sort of ShakeOut as they'll call
it in the morning of the day before is
also weight cut day and so there's some
other variables going on at those sports
but in
weightlifting day and a half to two days
of complete rest prior to competition is
pretty common powerlifters it's probably
more like two to five days powerlifters
really do like uh conserving their
energy is how I will say it strong men
more like four and then CrossFit
Highland more like again 2 days or so
prior to competition in terms of
intensity you will generally see this is
where some anomalies kick in and I
really want to highlight this because
what's clear from the endurance side of
the equation as you'll see is you almost
always want to keep intensity around but
that doesn't work when your sport is
lifting at high intensity so you
wouldn't want to lift say at 95% of your
one at Max for the three or 4 days prior
to powerlifting or weightlifting
competition it's too high but you could
certainly run at 100% of your VO2 max 3
or four days before that's totally fine
so it's a little bit of a different
things here so in these strength Sports
you will actually see intensity come
down a little bit during your taper and
that makes sense a lot of folks are
going to get up to like 85% maybe but
probably shut it down it's just too
damaging and too fatiguing to recover
from something like that in the in the
week of the competition
now in terms of volume though it is
actually really consistent weightlifter
is about a 40% reduction in volume
typically powerlifters 40 to maybe
60% strongman 45% Highland Games 34%
crossfitters 40% so it all lands right
in that 40 to 60% range that we talked
about earlier frequency is our last
variable here and we don't have anything
particularly interesting to say here
because it's exactly like we've
explained it's either going to the same
frequency or slightly reduced one thing
we haven't talked about is this volume
Peak and so what you'll tend to see for
weightlifters is that their highest
volume happens about five to six weeks
prior to competition it comes down from
that but they don't really hit their
taper until that 8we day but their
volume Peaks you know a month and a half
or so prior to competition and their
intensity is going to Peak about two to
two and a half weeks out as well so a
little tidbit I thought we could throw
on there that is uh I found valuable and
interesting in a couple of the papers
last thing here and this is really
important in the weightlifting
powerlifting Highland Games and other
research almost all of them had people
report when they asked them why did your
tapers fail in the
past you'll see an almost equal
distribution of people who said my taper
was too
long as well as people said my taper was
too short and so while I can give you
these sweeping recommendations that are
General the research is really
clear people report their taper failing
from an almost equal combination of
saying it was too long and Too Short
which is to say these guidelines should
be treated simply as that they are rough
starting points but please you have to
identify what works best for you and
your physiology which means you have to
compete a lot this is why practicing and
this is actually something that people
don't do a lot and it surprises me but
you should practice the taper routine
you should go through simulations and
see and document what exactly you're
doing and control it doing your Regional
events during your qualifiers and going
through these things as often as you can
and you will start to figure out for you
and your physiology and your life
situation what works best for you I
thought that was a really interesting
nugget that I wanted to pull out to help
you get the best for your taper because
while I can share with you research
that's going to Simply indicate what's
most likely to work and most people most
of the time but that's not you you and
you want to help impr perform you and
you want to help your clients and so for
that you need to take an individual
approach and make the best decisions
possible for them and that requires
practice and diligent note taking let's
move on now and talk about sprinting
speed I'm actually going to be really
short here there's a cool paper that
I'll Point your attention to uh it is a
training and development of elite Sprint
performance and integration of
scientific and best practices an
interesting paper from 2019 I think but
in that they lay out a specific 10day
protocol exactly what to do for the 10
days prior to competition it was based
on the work of Charlie Francis the
famous Sprint coach um Ben Johnson among
others and so I'll Point your attention
to that you can go see that exact
protocol but it's really not worth me
walking through it right now if you can
just go download it and read it yourself
but we don't really have much
information outside of that on optimal
practices for sprinters and taper so
we'll transition then now and talk about
what we do know about team
sports more data here most of it on
soccer rugby volleyball one particular
study and some basketball ones and
really it's the same rules as kind of
everybody else so we don't need to draw
any specific attention to this with one
exception and the reason I want to
highlight this is you will see with team
sports a need to pay attention to the
entire year such that most scientists
and the information is going to argue
you probably should have somewhere
between two to three planned tapers per
year and now this is particularly
relevant for college high school or even
Youth Sports if you're doing multiple
Sports at once if you're anything like
me and as a kid you started the year off
in football and then you rolled right
into basketball and then you rolled
right into baseball and then you rolled
right into your summer work and and
lifting hay bals and building roads and
things like that in the summer there was
really no taper it's probably smart if
you are competing year round whether
it's a single sport or multiple Sports
to have at least two to three planned
tapers throughout that time that's
probably the most interesting thing we
can pull out here that's a little bit
different from what we've already talked
about but the rest is very similar to
what we've already highlighted one other
little aspect is maintaining skill work
if you are a basketball player and you
got to make sure you're shot is on point
or a rugby player or whatever it else it
is make sure that you are prioritizing
your skill work work during your taper
and so you want to minimize volume and
the way to do that is to reduce the
conditioning and reduce you basic
movement stuff and keep your volume
through your skill work so you keep your
skill sharp but you can keep volume down
you move at a play speed you try to hit
the ball as hard as you would in a game
or close to it or you try to run or jump
or do those things close but then you
just don't do a ton of it so skills stay
sharp speed and power and strength stay
high but you red reduce that cumulative
fatigue by lowering the volume finally
here to round us out with what we'll
call endurance exercise I'll point you
to one more review article that
highlights this the effects of tapering
on performance and endurance athletes a
systematic review and meta analysis
really great covers a lot of stuff in
that they went over a whole bunch of
papers and boiled it down to about 14
and found that pretty pronounced effects
improvements on time trial performance
time to exhaustion no real changes as
we've described earlier in V2 Max or
running economy and most of the athletes
did a 40 to 60% volume drop and the
duration was somewhere like 7 to 21 days
hopefully by now you've learned a lot
about plateauing peing and overtraining
also Avid listeners are probably clear
to the fact that I traditionally end the
show going over the three eyes so what
to investigate how to interpret that and
then how to intervene on that but I've
chosen to not do it in this episode
because I've actually just weaved much
of that stuff in along with the content
as we went along and so I want to finish
on that but what I want to do is finish
on something that a lot of you are
interested in and that is many listeners
are either aspiring to or currently
working directly with high performance
athletes I thought it would then be
helpful for many of you in fact if you
don't want to work that you're still
interested on what are these people
really doing so I'd like to share with
you some insights of what happens at the
highest level level when we have to
monitor when we have to predict when
we've got one shot every four years or
maybe one attempt in a career to play
for a World Series or an NBA
championship or something like that but
then boil it also down and say okay what
are some other specific examples that
many of you can use to pay attention to
all these things along the way I've
given plenty of hints and direct tactics
before but I wanted to summarize all
that for you as we wrap up so let's dive
into it and see what that looks like now
getting it started if you dive into the
world of performance you will see almost
everybody is tracking load somehow they
are tracking mileage or they're using
GPS trackers to see how much area we
covered in practice they have some sort
of physiology going and so this world
can be really extensive really quickly
but I wanted to give you a quick
overview of what that looks like
traditionally most high performance
directors are measuring at least one
thing from three specific areas area one
is what we call tracking so this could
be things like LPS's or Imus or GPS
could be as simple as pitch count or
mileage or something like that so what
is the actual person doing work-wise
number two what's the performance
response so how's the game play what's
their physical strength a lot of coaches
will use things like a vertical jump and
these are traditionally being tested
every single day really really common
for people to come in do a vertical jump
jump test every single day and that's
telling them where their system is at
overall so they're tracking total work
they're measuring performance again
almost daily if not three to four times
per week and then the third big category
is what we'll call physiology and
psychology so they're looking at various
markers of Central or peripheral nervous
system this could be a tap test could be
HRV score resting heart rate something
like that they may be looking at
biomarkers I've given you examples
earlier some are doing blood markers
multiple times per week some are
salivary some are just doing big blood
draws before mid postseason something
like that could be sleep could be mood
could be RP or anything like that but
you could basically say most people
doing it well are taking at least one
thing from all three of these areas if
that's within your capabilities right
now depending on your budget or interest
I would strongly recommend a similar
approach the Technologies the tools the
tactics are infinite within this
category and always growing and so we
didn't have time and I don't even know
how you would attempt to cover all of
them in all these areas I think probably
more appropriately is just to think
about categorically making something
that represents one metric from each of
these areas and choose your technology
and frequency and all that based upon
your budget and scenario now when budget
is of no concern like I've been
fortunate to have in several scenarios
in my coaching career you can get wild
and so it can look something cool like
this we have recently completed a PL
project that we call the human digital
twin where data collection was we'll
just say obnoxious and we're able to
collect everything from five large areas
area one is what we'll call physiology
and this is both Baseline and acute
responses like we've been talking about
autonomic nervous system blood urine
stool saliva sweat hair muscle size and
symmetry muscle quality body composition
a ton of different areas that are giving
us Baseline physiology area two
performance both again Baseline and
acute responses strength power movement
quality we're talking about fully
digitizing movement full kinetics and
kinematics everything that's happening
in practice and in performance of every
movement endurance uh portable metabolic
carts Reaction Time neurological firing
fatigue cognition Performance Physical
mental all up and down the chain all
being done based line as well as acute
challenges area number three environment
so we're looking at water quality
Plastics air quality everything else we
can get our hands on number four
psychology stress load mental load
mental health daily acute chronic so on
and so forth and then finally recovery
sleep architecture
resilience uh amount of time and depth
in each sleep stage everything we can
possibly get out in those areas we were
able to take all those data and now put
those into a single model and use very
Advanced um Computing if you will to
create a digital replica of these
people's physiology and then from there
we can actually create and run
experiments on the digital twin and
figure out how this person is going to
respond best to training nutrition
supplementation back offs sleep
interventions whatever else we need to
run that said what do you do right now
if you don't have any access or want to
use anything like that step number one I
would recommend if you're concerned
about plateaus or overtraining or
non-functional overreaching is to rule
out things that are causing problems
right now meaning if you feel like your
performance is going down or you're
recovering make sure you don't have some
sort of viral infection you have a fever
maybe you're experiencing depression
your diet's crappy you're not sleeping
you're drinking a little bit more than
you thought there's a work stressor
that's bringing you down let's just make
sure nothing else is actually happening
that would be explaining these short to
moderate term dips that are really not
an issue of your physiology and being
overtrained it's something that's
actually directly explaining it if
that's the case do your best to remove
those and we don't have anything else to
worry about so that's my starting tip
number one that everyone should be able
to do from there at the beginning of the
episode I talked about my MVP strategy
and I'll expand a little bit on that
right now number one I tend to pick
things that I call Early responders so
if you only have the budget or ability
to measure one or two things I'm
probably not going to look at things
like a resting heart rate why it is a
good sign it will tell you but that is a
low responder it's not super sensitive
so the change in resting heart rate
won't be dramatic and it's late in the
game things have already happened in
your blood we can see things have
already happened in something like your
HRV heart rate response is going to be
weeks delayed you're probably into the
into the problem already and I like to
stop it before it starts so I like an
early
responder HRV is a great example yeah
this is heart rate variability this is a
good indication of where you're at
overall balance of how much time you
spending in parasympathetic or down
regulation versus sympathetic or up
regulation okay neither one of those are
bad but if you're spending all your time
in down regulation your HRV will be
suppressed and you're going to see that
now HRV is far more sensitive than
something like a resting heart rate okay
so it will tell you insights much sooner
but it requires a trend do not make any
judgment or decision based for your
current exercise based on a single day's
HRV if you talk to experts in these
areas that have done this for decades
and have thousands of data points or
thousands of athletes and millions of
data points they're going to tell you
hey look we're looking for a three to 5
day maybe 7day maybe 10day Trend before
we're super worried about it okay so HRV
would be better than resting heart rate
in my opinion if if you had to pick one
this is where I think things like blood
work will tell you you're going to see
signs immediately that this happens and
you will see them in my experience
before HRV starts to move and before
resting heart rate if you don't have
access to that another good one I've
talked about a lot recently is
respiratory rate now respiratory rate is
pretty sensitive as well and I feel like
and I don't have scientific data to
support this there is some but it's not
a landslide this is now my personal
coaching experience I feel like this
show signs sooner I can tell you this
from my physiology if I wake up and my
respiratory rate is more than probably
one and a half uh breaths per minute
higher than my average 100% something
happened that night or I'm getting sick
or something else happens so my body
responds really well to that and the
athletes we've tracked the people in our
coaching programs non-athletes it is
lined up pretty well so I like to go
after that one first and that is not
particularly hard to measure one thing I
would like to clarify Maybe haven't
talked and we'll probably do full
episodes later in the show about things
like HRV but this is nice because unlike
a blood biomarker where it's really only
telling you information about that area
HRV is a systemic marker so it's telling
you that idea of where your entire
system is at and so a lot of people make
the argument I don't need all those
other things you talked about in your
human digital twin if I can get 80%
there with that one single metric and
you might be right you can get pretty
close with something like an HRV so
that's the advantage of doing that it
cuts down data collection gives you a
broad stroke idea of what's happening
the entire physiology it's
nonspecific but it will give huge
advantage to people that are restricted
to data collection okay so a lot of
value there to kind of give you one more
little personal insight and this is
actually really cool a paper from uh
friends of mine in Stockholm uh Philip
Larsson his group out there did a really
cool overtraining study and one of the
things that they found from that that I
thought was super practical is the study
found actually impaired mitochondrial
function with overtraining and we saw
some glucos dis regulation and things
like that but what I thought was super
interesting is they found this if you
take somebody who's exercise trained and
expose them to a standard workout we've
talked about this now several times and
their heart rate is the same or
lower but the respiratory rate is higher
they you have a very very strong
likelihood that their nervous system is
fried that they're overworked or however
you want to phrase this see typically
the more fit you become the lower your
heart rate response is to a given
workout right the same training speed is
no longer as challenging so your resting
heart rate comes down because your
stroke volume's gone up we talked about
that in detail in our cardiovascular
episode however a lot of people will do
the same exact workout if they notice
their heart ratees higher then it's like
oh man maybe something's going on and it
might be but if you look at your data
and you don't feel great you feel junky
and you realize your heart rate is the
same or maybe even
lower and you might be thinking oh my
gosh I guess my physiology is fine it
might be but it also might not be and
the way to differentiate that is if you
see that that heart rate again is the
same or lower than it normally is but
your respiratory rate is higher that's a
pretty good indication that the system
is is pretty fried pretty tired you're
breathing harder than you need to be
your resting heart rate's lower you're
not responding like you should be to a
stressor and maybe some back off is
needed in the future to finish this off
here what I'd like to do is clarify a
handful of things you can do that I call
acute and chronic actions if you do feel
like you're in the hole a little bit we
never specifically laid this out but
number one is rest so if you are
actually overtrained or close or
nonfunctional or otherwise
the most important and direct thing you
can do is recover and rest but there's
actually
subcategories that fit into multiple
areas this include things like food
supplementation thermal stress breath
work what I call Brain distractions
light rest sleep and a bunch of other
things that can help you crawl back out
of this and maybe we'll do an entire
show just on these and jump straight to
them but I call some of these aute
and
chronic for a particular reason so let's
take an example of something like
supplementation if you look at say
caffeine if you feel kind of low energy
and fatigued today caffeine will help
that acutely but it's not going to
chronically recover you from
overtraining so that wouldn't be a
chronic responder you might have to do
something more like sleep more or reduce
training or try something that has been
talked about a lot recently like biof
feedback or journaling social connection
work on recovering hormone status things
like that might be needed to actually
chronically fix the problem relative to
actually giving you some shortterm
resolution one that I has been
documented actually from the CrossFit
over training study that I thought was
very interesting comes from carbohydrate
so one of the things that they noticed
that jumped out really clearly amongst
those folks that were
experiencing more overtraining or
overtraining like symptom responses is
carbohydrate inti was about three times
lower in those individuals so just
simply making sure you're not dropping
below say 5 grams per kilogram of body
weight per day of
carbohydrate when you're doing Advanced
and high levels training if possible is
probably a good idea so that will help
actually in fact that's one of the
things we turn to quite often is if
people are just feeling low energy we'll
give them more calories if you can
afford that okay so there's lots of
tools and tactics I actually have an
entire
table here that I've built out perhaps
we'll put that up in our show notes ah
I'll do it all right I'll just commit to
it right now it'll be up there and you
can look at all these things some that I
call parlor tricks so this is where
motivational quotes or music or a movie
or something will come in those are not
going to fix your overtraining problems
but they might give you an acute boost
of energy if that's really all you're
experiencing so as I said at the very
very beginning because performance is
not one thing and stress is not one
thing there's not one thing to track and
there's not one thing to do to solve
them you really need to think carefully
about in my situation what's probably
causing my largest constraint what's my
biggest area of opportunity and what's
within my reason and preferences and
abilities and skills in terms of what
solution I want to deploy maybe you want
to use more supplementation maybe you
want to use more thermal stress like hot
or cold or nutrition or you need to just
sleep more or combinate of all those
things I hope that this episode just let
you know you have a lot of options
that's one of the major goals I have
with this show and with my entire
strategy for science communication is to
not make people feel like they have to
do certain things if that's not really
the case and so you got a lot of causes
for overtraining or plateauing and peing
that means you also have a lot of
opportunity for Solutions and pick the
ones that are most appropriate for you
in your situation thank you for joining
for today's episode our goal is to share
exciting scientific Insight that helps
you perform at your absolute best if the
show resonates with you and you want to
help ensure this information remains
free and accessible to anyone in the
world there are a few ways that you can
support first you can subscribe to the
show on YouTube Spotify and apple and on
Apple and Spotify you can leave up to a
five-star review given that we're a new
podcast subscribing and leaving a review
really does help us a lot second please
check out our sponsors the show would
not exist without them and they really
are exceptional products and services
and then finally you can share today's
episode with a friend who you think
would enjoy it if you have any content
questions or suggestions please put
those in the comment section on YouTube
I really do try to read these and see
what you have to say if you have yet to
sign up for our monthly newsletter you
can do so at perform podcast.com our
newsletter provides episode summaries
with the key takeaways for each and
every episode of the podcast this
includes topics like how to improve your
V2 Max how to build muscle mass and
muscle strength how to optimize your
sleep performance and much more to sign
up just go to perform podcast.com click
newsletter at the top of the screen and
then enter your email address once you
sign up you receive access to all of our
newsletters I use my Instagram and
Twitter also exclusively for scientific
communication so those are great places
to follow along for more learning my
handle is Dr Andy Galpin on both
platforms thank you for listening and
never forget in the famous words of Bill
Bowerman if you have a body you're an
athlete